[Music]
welcome to this business Central launch
event session for 2023 release Wave 2
introducing analyze data on lists and
queries
we have a tightly packed
agenda and the most important thing is
the first the world is
changing what's that let's
see then we talk about analyzing data on
list pages on queries um how you can
share a data analysis definition with a
coworker or friend how you can turn off
the feature if you really want to do
that and um and then some learning
resources and
Goos so what does this mean the world is
changing well the world is changing in
many many different ways for this
session because we're talking about
reporting and analytics this is of
course the world of reporting and data
analysis is
changing now in this session it's very
important that uh that we make this
distinction
distinction the word reporting in
business Central means three different
things analytical reports processing
only reports and printable documents in
this session we only cover analytical
reports okay very important not the
other
two so it's the world that is changing
for
analytics in
organizations there are different needs
to analyze data depending on on what
kind of role you have
typically if you look at an
organizational diagram here the further
you go up towards
leadership the further you probably need
to have your data
aggregated so that staff people working
on operational uh sorry on
processes probably need pretty detailed
data whereas middle management typically
want Trends and summaries and in the
leadership team you probably mostly want
performance data kpis and so on so that
also means the typical ways to consume
data is or the tools you use for your
analytics needs change on the different
role in your organization typical of
course is that it's not that people
working in leadership only deal with
kpis and dashboards and financial
reports but it's just the typical way to
consume this
data so we worked with this definition
of different tools for different needs
to build a vision for analytics and
Reporting and the main thing in this
vision for business Central is that
analytics is build for online
consumption not for print remember again
this is not document reporting this is
analytics or analytical reporting so
online consumption is the way we want to
move things forward and we have three
different pillars to this Vision the
first one is the way your customers cons
or users consume
data we want business Central to have
outof thee boox reporting and and
analytics solutions for the Core
Business scenarios in the product number
two we want to enable that most of the
analytical needs that users have are
simply covered with no code or low codes
Solutions and
three that customers have easy access to
data for advanced bi and Analytics
of course part of this Vision the
partner Community is key so isvs should
also be able to deliver analytics and
remember this is not document reporting
this presentation has nothing to do with
the documents uh that you use for
invoices and so on okay only for
analytics so let me show you some
features we built in this space the
first is how to analyze data on list
Pages you can think about analyze data
on list Pages as before you run a report
you get a PDF and if you need to do
something else a different type of
analysis you would need to run the
report with different parameters get a
new PDF and so on in this new world we
want to enable self-service data
analysis directly in the
client and with analyzed data on lists
you get just that you can quickly
extract insights you can design data or
analysis your way with different tabs on
the data where the grouping uh filters
and so on is is local to that
analysis and then you can save your
analysis for later it will just stay
there so the next time you go go to the
list it's there and you can pick up your
analysis this was in public preview in
2023 release wave one and you needed to
enable it under feature
Management in this release wave this is
generally
available where Microsoft we abbreviate
everything so generally available we
call that GA it's the same thing so the
feature is enabled for all users you
don't need to use feat feature
management anymore the feature can be
turned off either by a developer who
says this is not something you can
analyze or with a permission I'll come
back to the permission part and not only
can
users save reports for later they can
actually share them with co-workers and
friends I'll show you that later as
well we also listen to feedback from the
public preview so we did some a few
small improvements to the user interface
first of all to discover this better we
open all make sure that the analysis
menus are always open the first time you
go to a page and then that persistence
will also take place for each of your
analysis menus so they open the men the
analysis menus are open closed depending
on how you want it for that analysis
then in the public preview we were a bit
cautious about the data size so we put a
limit on 100,000 rows uh on a list where
you could uh load that data and then
that's it if you had more data you would
need to do a pre-filtering on the list
before you went into this new mode of
analyzing data not anymore with the with
23 2023 release Wave 2 we removed
completely this limitation and you can
allow you can analyze as much data as
you want of course if you have tons of
data it might take a little longer to
load the
page and then also as a new thing in
this release we added the ability to
analyze data not only on lists but also
on quy objects and I'll show you some
examples of that in this
presentation but let's maybe take a look
at how analyzed data on lists look in
the 2023 release Wave 2 all right so I'm
on the RO Center and um let's try to
first of all analyze one of our ledgers
maybe I'm interested in the customer
Ledger entry table or customer Ledger
entries because I want to analyze my
sales data so if I search for customer
Ledger entries let's see if we find that
page this is a list page and um
this is the normal list you know but
then if you tockle this analyze button
here it takes the page into the analysis
mode and this opens up a completely new
UI that allows you to analyze slice and
dice the data you notice that the first
time you go into this on a page um the
menus are here are enabled and there's
an analysis one create it for you if I
um just click here to remove things and
maybe just add a customer number and a
document number let's put a customer
number here and a document number down
here and let's say I I'm fine with this
for now it's a silly analysis but uh but
that's how it is I hide my choice and um
and I go back to my um my role Center so
let's uh let me go
to back to the customer Ledger or sorry
to the role Center then next time I go
to the same list customer Ledger entries
let's see if we can find it
here first of all you notice that
business Central remembers your choice
of this toggle so if the Last Action you
did was to analyze data on this list it
actually persists that choice and the
second choice business Central chose to
persist was the that the menus are now
no longer expanded so the the choice of
analysis mode or not on a page as well
as uh the initial opening of these is
something we thought at least we we
heard from the our um UI experiments and
our UI testing that this would make the
feature easier to
discover but let me open up the menu
again and let's let's just try a few
things here so let me uh for instance
I'm interested in in sales and maybe I
want to look at sales amount in dollars
uh Group by customer and document number
now I can just easily see which
customers uh bought uh what and the
invoice number
and if I then want to maybe pivot this
and see the posting when was this posted
um then I can I I can see the posting
date has a date hierarchy of a year
quarter month maybe I want to pull in
the posting date year and maybe the
quarter into my Pivot here and then I
can uh let's just get rid of the few of
these measures here I just want this
some sum of
amount here you go and now I have my sum
of amount by
quarter um last year and this year but
very very easy for me to as a customer
or a user to to write my own mini
reports many users would actually see
data analysis as reporting tool and they
would call
these my sales report
okay so that's in a nutshell data
analysis directly in the client it uh
it's on live data no replicated data
security model is preserved and uh
totally no code analysis ad hoc analysis
on your
data the next thing we added in this
wave was not only can you do data
analysis on lists pages but you can also
do it on query objects query objects in
the past was something that was done by
developers to speed up code but now you
can use a query object as the data
foundation for this new way of doing ad
hoc analysis or
reporting so it you had always in in
business Central the ability to open a
query with on the URL with Slash
question mark query equals the query
ID but the new thing is that this now
comes with the same analysis chle and it
opens the same UI now on queries let's
try to just to see uh that it's going to
be a boring demo because it looks
exactly the same way as data analysis on
lists all right so for this demo I I
created um a query and I'm using this
URL query equals and then the ID of this
of course that's not the way users will
interact with this but just for you to
see the UI so I will open
this right and now um you can see my
query here is called analyze your invent
inventory and I even added a teaching
tip for it um show help actually shows
the teaching tip and I can even add uh
links to the doc specific links to a
documentation for this query so that's a
way to document a query so that users
can find it even more
useful in this particular example I took
something on inventory on items and I
joined that in the query with location
details so you know you can notice here
that I have item description and
location let's find a Mexican chair and
now instead of um the normal location
codes these uppercase thingies you can
actually use the location names from the
location from the related table that's
what I joined in in my query and I can
see now that East
Warehouse has remaining quantity of
three main one and West Warehouse 6
which means the Outsource Logistics
location uh there's nothing happening
there and you can see these are the
elements in my query I have location
code from the item list or item table
but I also have location name City and
country that I joined in my query and
enables me now to do analysis on in
inventory based on location and anything
else you might want to add in your query
you can suddenly analyze on with the
same user
interface so a few features came in a
bit late in our release so they are
likely available in version
23.1 um queries are just any other UI
element that will now show up in report
or role Explorer and they are also
searchable in tell me just like you
would search for a report or search for
a page you can now search for a query
and and they will show up in the places
where we want like to to make content
discoverable so role Explorer what's
that Beast what's that and what are
these new links if you go to tell me or
on the role Center main role Center so
you have something called exploring
reports or all
reports these are the foundation for a
new con concept where we want reporting
content to be much more discoverable in
business Central we got feedback from
users who said business Central doesn't
come with any reports okay well if you
click on that report Explorer and if you
also remember to expand all business
Central will remember your choice so uh
so it only need to do that once you
actually see that there's a lot of
analytical capabilities is in business
Central build in so that's part of the
vision you remember the vision build in
analytical content for every use case or
every main feature in business Central
it's right here and we're adding to that
uh going to going to add to that with
queries uh and with reports and other
reporting
artifacts all
right another thing we added in this
release wave was ability to share an
analysis definition with a
coworker so on the analysis tab menu
I'll show you in a minute you can share
a link to the analysis you did as a user
with a
friend and a quick tip here is of course
these links you can put them anywhere in
teams or on a web page or in onee or
whatever you like uh and they're
basically quick uh click once installers
for for
analysis uh so let me uh let me just
show you actually I'll just show you
here it's the same demo so here I have
an income statement by month analysis I
did and uh you can see that I if I open
this tab uh menu I can copy link and
then I get a menu where I'm able either
to say this link is for the specific
company or this is
a company agnostic link and you can copy
then and you can share that so instead
of showing you the the sharing I would
actually like to demo The Click On's
idea so let me go and show you that if
you go to
aka.ms
slbc data analysis let's do
that then you come to our reposit open
source repository of all kinds of of
sample code for this particular sample
Le code we added some click ones
scenarios where you can just try out
this idea about click ones these only
work in the in 2023 release Wave 2 uh
but here are some different scenarios
described um how to do it in Click Click
and like an instruction of how to do it
but also a click ones like tried and
business Central so let's let's not go
for finance let's go about Finance but
let's take the sales report here sales
sorry this one here uh the description
says get an overview of the customers
that purchase the most or that owe the
most I'm interested in this and I would
like to try it out so instead of redoing
the analysis by hand I simply click here
to create so it says control click let's
open that in a new browser Tab and let's
see what this brings to the table
and look create an open uh analysis View
and it proposed uh or it told me look
this could be a good name for this
analysis tab total sales and remaining
amounts I'm happy with this I'll click
okay and there you go now you have a
data analysis from a friend the total
sales and remaining amounts seems like
we are doing something on customer name
and document number the invoices and
then uh sum of remaining amount sum of
sales I'm happy with that um so it
opened up with it this data analysis
opened I don't want that but my sales
report here I actually want this if I go
out of data analysis and back to the
customer Ledger and then let's say
tomorrow or lunch next day I go back
here you can see that business Central
has persisted my menu choice of still
analyzing on my sales report but the
other one here has persisted that I
actually don't want the menu item to be
persisted or or opened it will just be
like that so this is how you can share
an analysis with a friend um using these
click ones or create a URL and then once
you click it it's available uh for that
other person you're not sharing in the
sense that if I share with you and I
change my definition
your definition will change once you
take my link and copy it it will become
your uh your own version of that and you
can then change that if you want to
rename if you want to whatever you want
to do with that it's your analysis and
it's disconnected from my it's just a
copy the final feature we added is
ability to turn off like why would you
want to do that with such a wonderful
feature well some customers don't want
all their employees to have open an
Excel feature similarly they don't want
this just easy to analyze and copy all
the data out so we added a new
permission uh a new system permission
called Data analysis exec or execute and
with this uh new permission set you if
you have this you're allowed to do data
analysis on everything where you have uh
permission on the object if you want to
to revoke this from users you do it the
normal way you create a new permission
set including everything they should do
and then you exclude this new permission
and then suddenly they cannot do data
analysis
anymore okay
resources first of all as I mentioned
this
aka.ms slbc data
analysis it gives you some ideas uh to
try out out with customers or or with
with co-workers and maybe kind of give
you some indication of how to get
started um we I think we put in
scenarios for 15 different ways of using
this across Finance Sales Inventory even
uh a little bit of compliance so take a
look and see if there's a scenario that
match what you like and uh and we'll see
if I'll try to get some of these click
one scenarios in there as well so so
it's not only the description but
actually just click and
try and then just going back to the
world is changing in reporting and
specifically in analytical
reporting let's stop this like if you're
a customer or if you are a consultant
and the customer asks can you build me a
report let's stop asking sure what
columns you have and where would you
like to put them and let's open the RDL
designer stop doing that
instead start asking the customer what
is it that you need to analyze and for
what because once you know the
analytical requirements and maybe know a
little bit about where in the
organization this user is uh is
operating then choose a tool of choice
that might be a report but maybe
something complet completely else maybe
for kbis powerbi and embedding powerbi
is the thing or as we saw in this
presentation the query lists ad hoc
analysis might just be the reports that
they want but it's not a traditional
business Central a report because it's
just a definition of things for queries
it would be what are the kind of what is
the data set I need to mesh up for you
dear customer so that you're unblocked
with your ad hoc analysis and if Excel
is important and or if the customer is
really skilled with Excel maybe build
them an Al data set in a report and then
tell them look do all the self-service
you want for your layouts it might be
this is probably a mix between low code
and no code and probably some customers
will be very Savvy with Excel and it
will be very not even low code but very
code but all of that do done uh in Excel
by the customer or by the
user so
Goos most important thing take away from
this understand analytics requirements
stop developing reports and start
supporting analytical
needs as a consultant or developer maybe
start learning a little bit about
powerbi powerbi
is here to stay business intelligence
and er they go together ER is about
processing supporting business processes
business's intelligence about insights
on business processes they go together
and powerbi is a really good tool to do
that kind of especially the on the top
level of the organizational
hierarchy start learning about Al
queries if if you thought Al queries was
just about performance tuning it's not
anymore we're changing the game for this
we're investing more in queries over the
next years quaries as a powerful tomb to
measure up data and that means instead
of building me a report it might just be
build me a query and I'm I'm unblocked
thank
you and finally start also learned about
or design data sets especially for Excel
layouts again that could be that instead
of buil me a report it's it's going to
be buil me a report data set and
especially for these build me things the
requirements there's a there's a an
relevant launch session specifically for
that which is called what's new in
powerbi and reporting for developers so
much more content of how you can help
customers building content of these
types you might also want to look into
uh other productivity features in the
web client if you like this kind of
content and
um and also the what's new on adding
existing uh table fields to optimize PES
is is also a way to do ad hog analysis
uh just um doing it on list
Pages for General resources Yammer is
the place where we take this discussions
we can do it on Twitter X as well all
AKA links are covered on the BC all AKA
so that's the one AKA URL to rule them
all if you have ideas for new features
or improvements BC ideas is your friend
and finally everything we talk about in
business Central launch events is also
covered in the business central office
hours they are also recorded and
available there and with that thank you
so much I hope you have a great business
Central launch event with great sessions
and hopefully parties around the world
with partner thank
you